Guide to the Anita Travers Thompson family papers 1884-1979
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Anita Travers Thompson family papers
1884-1979
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-2681 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 232
Thompson, Anita Travers, 1901-1988
1.2 linear feet of shelf space
This collection (1884-1924, 1978) consists of papers of Anita Thompson; her parents John Jacob Thompson and Sarah Travers; her brother Stewart McKinley Thompson; and her aunts Anna Travers, and Margaret Travers Ginste. The papers concern family matters; the Rock Springs coal mine near Sand Coulee, Montana; the Canyon Ferry Dam; student life at Montana State College of Agriculture and Mechanical Arts in Bozeman; and miscellany.
Biographical Note:
John Jacob Thompson was born near Toronto, Canada, in 1862. He moved to North Dakota at the age of twenty-two and then to Great Falls, Montana, in 1890. There he worked as a clerk at the Park Hotel and in a laundry. Thompson established the Great Falls Produce Company in 1893, and operated the business until 1899, when he sold it and established another of similar nature. In 1899 he purchased the Rock Springs coal mine near Sand Coulee. Thompson married Sarah Travers of Owens Sound, Canada, in 1896. The couple had two children, Stewart and Anita. Sarah Travers had two sisters, Margaret Ginste of Dillon, Montana, and Anna of Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan and Great Falls, Montana. John Jacob Thompson died in 1906, and Sarah Travers Thompson died in 1907.
Stewart McKinley Thompson was born in 1896. He attended Great Falls High School and graduated from Montana State College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts in Bozeman with a degree in electrical engineering in 1921. His wife's name was Maude. Stewart Thompson died in mysterious circumstances near the Canyon Ferry power plant, where he worked, in 1923.
Anita Travers Thompson graduated from Great Falls High School in 1919, attended Montana State College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts from 1919 to 1921, and graduated with a B.S. in pharmacy from the University of Michigan in 1924. She was certified as a registered pharmacist in Montana in 1927, at which time she resided in Jordan. She moved to Tacoma, Washington, in 1929, and worked for Pay Less Drugs from 1932 until at least 1968.
This collection consists of the papers of John Jacob Thompson, Sarah Travers Thompson, Stewart McKinley Thompson, Anita Travers Thompson, Anna Travers, Margaret Travers Ginste, and J.J. Ginste.
The papers of John Jacob Thompson (1884-1907) include correspondence, primarily incoming with some outgoing to his wife, which discusses: financial matters, especially the payment of rent in Great Falls; business; family; Great Falls; California; etc. Thompson's papers also include naturalization papers, a bank book, a diary/note book, a land sale contract, and a dues book of the Modern Woodman of America.
Sarah Travers Thompson's papers (1907-1908) include correspondence and invoices concerning John Jacob Thompson's estate and funeral.
Anna Travers' papers (1908-1914) include correspondence and invoices concerning the boarding of Sarah Travers Thompson in a sanatarium and her funeral, and John Jacob Thompson's estate.
Margaret Travers Ginste's papers (1914-1923) include financial papers; outgoing correspondence, primarily to Stewart McKinley Thompson concerning family matters and events in Great Falls; and one letter from Maude Thompson.
J.J. Ginste's papers (1921-1926) consist of a letter from the Montana Power Company regarding Stewart McKinley Thompson's death; a motor registration and certificate of insurance.
Stewart McKinley Thompson's papers (1912-1925) include correspondence with Anita Travers Thompson, Margaret Travers Ginste, his friends, and future wife concerning student life and his work; diaries with brief comments about the weather, recreational activities, school, work at the substation at Canyon Ferry, etc.; school grade reports; union and lodge cards; financial records; etc.
The papers of Anita Travers Thompson (1904-1925, 1978) include correpondence with Stewart McKinley Thompson and Margaret Travers Ginste about student life; high school grade reports, college dance cards, invitations to parties, place cards, programs for concerts and plays, diaries, school certificates, etc.
by subgroup and series
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
Photographs of the Thompson Family are in the Photo Archives. Artifacts have been transferred to the Museum.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Women--Education--Montana
Bozeman (Mont.)--Social life and customs
Great Falls (Mont.)
Great Falls (Mont.)--Social life and customs
Sand Coulee (Mont.)
Montana
Elementary and Secondary Education
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Anita Travers Thompson
  - Biographical Materials
    - Includes writings on Thompson family geneaology; birth and death certificates for Anita Travers Thompson, 1901-1988, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - General Correspondence
    - Correspondence (Margaret Ginste, aunt; J.J. Ginste, uncle; John Jacob Thompson, father; Sarah Thompson, mother; Stewart Thompson, brother), 1908-1923, 1979 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Diaries
    - Diaries, 1915; 1920; 1925; 1927 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - School Notes and Records
    - Annual (Martha Cook Hall, University of Michigan); commencement programs; report cards; miscellany, 1924 (Box-folder 1 / 4-6)
  - Miscellany
    - Autograph book, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - Playbills (performances in Great Falls and Bozeman, Montana; and Detroit, Michigan), 1919-1924, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 9)
    - Programs (performances in Great Falls and Bozeman, Montana; and Detroit, Michigan), 1919-1924 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
    - Professional records (licences and certificates of achievement), 1927, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
    - Scrapbook, 1919-1921 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - Printed Material
    - The Rho Chi Society, 1972 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - Clippings
    - Clippings (re High school graduation and "Pharmacist of the Month award"), 1919; 1972 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
- John Jacob Thompson
  - General Correspondence
    - Correspondence (A.H. Cramer; Great Northern Railway Line; T.H. Neeley; Sara Thompson, wife; William W. Thompson, brother; Anita Thompson, daughter; Stewart Thompson, son), 1892-1907 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - Diaries
    - Diary, 1884-1886 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Financial Records
    - Account book and draft receipts: Great Falls National Bank, 1898-1907 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
    - Dues book: Preferred Mutual Accident Association, 1898-1905 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Legal Documents
    - Leases and Agreements (miscellaneous), 1894-1901 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - Miscellany
    - Certificates and license (miscellaneous), 1889-1890; 1904,1929 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
    - Letterhead: Feed, Produce and Commission (Box-folder 2 / 11)
- Sarah Travers Thompson
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Correspondence (T.H. Neeley), 1907-1908 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - Financial Records
    - Bills of sale: John James Thompson estate, 1907-1908 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
  - Legal Documents
    - Benefits statement: Modern Woodmen of America, 1907 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
- Stewart McKinley Thompson
  - General Correspondence
    - Correspondence (J.J. Ginste, uncle; Margaret Ginste, aunt; Maude Lawson; Helena M.S.C. Alumni Club; Reorganization Committee of the American Bank and Trust Company; Anita Thompson, sister), 1908-1923 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
  - Diaries
    - Diaries, 1908-1921 (Box-folder 2 / 16)
  - Financial Records
    - Tax records, 1909; 1919- 1920 (Box-folder 2 / 17)
  - School Notes and Records
    - Annual (Montanan, Montana State College), 1921 (Box-folder 2 / 18)
    - School records and mementos (Report cards, diploma, commencement announcements, etc.), 1904-1922 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
  - Miscellany
    - Lodge and Union cards: International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers; King Solomon's Lodge #9, Masonic, 1919; 1923 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
- Margaret Travers Ginste
  - General Correspondence
    - Correspondence (J.J. Ginste, husband; Stewart Thompson, nephew), 1914-1923 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
  - Financial Records
    - Listing of expenditures; receipts, 1914-1918 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
  - Legal Documents
    - Indenture; insurance certificate, 1926, 1929 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
  - School Notes/Records
    - Grades from Normal School in Dillon, Montana, 1920-1922 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
- J.J. Ginste
  - Legal Documents
    - Montana Power Company re final check, 1923, n.d. (Box-folder 3 / 7)
    - Motor registration; insurance certificate, 1921, 1926 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
- Anna Travers
  - General Correspondence
    - Correspondence (Portland Sanitorium; Anita Travers Thompson, niece; Sarah Thompson, sister; Stewart Thompson, nephew; William Thompson), 1908-1913 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
  - Financial Records
    - Receipt: Great Falls Music House, 1910 (Box-folder 3 / 10)
  - Legal Documents
    - Contracts: John Jacob and Sarah Travers Thompson estates (Anna Travers, executor), 1908-1914 (Box-folder 3 / 11)
    - Payment contract (legal work in Anna Travers vs Dell Hurd et. al.), 1910 (Box-folder 3 / 12)